Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
本系列基于并受锡吕·玛塔吉·涅玛拉·德维 (Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi) 教导的启发，
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
旨在探索两个相互关联领域之间的 进化关系，
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
这两个领域在物质和精微层面上 表达了人类的觉知。
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
它致力于阐明，关于当前科学 对人体神经解剖学 (特别是自主神经系统) 的理解，
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
与传统瑜伽文献中描述的
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
“精微能量系统” 之间的复杂相互作用。
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最后本系列试图带领观众 踏上这段探索之旅，
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
通过锡吕·玛塔吉·尼玛拉·德维的冥想法， 去体验这些关系。
Thanks everyone for joining us today.
感谢大家今天参加我们的节目。
In our previous episode, we started on an exploration
在上一集中，我们开始探索
into the fascinating intersection of neuroscience and spirituality
神经科学与灵性之间 精彩的交汇点，
with Dr. Ashish Pradhan, who is a distinguished leader in neurology
与我们对话的是阿希什·普拉丹医生， 他是一位杰出的神经学
and cardiovascular medicine, renowned for his cutting-edge work
和心血管医学领域的领袖， 他在人本治疗（patient-centric care) 方面，以其前沿性工作
and strategic leadership in patient-centric care.
和战略领导力而闻名。
He emphasized the importance of understanding the complexities of the nervous system
他强调理解 神经系统复杂性的重要性，
as a foundation for exploring the spiritual aspects of being human.
以此作为探索人类灵性层面的基础。
Dr. Pradhan also talked to us about the brain's evolutionary journey,
普拉丹医生还与我们谈到了 大脑的进化之旅，
highlighting the fascinating adaptations that have shaped its structure and function.
并强调了那些塑造其结构与功能的 精彩应性变化。
And today we welcome all of you to this second episode of our enlightening series
今天，我们欢迎大家 收看我们这个启发性系列的第二集，
with the esteemed Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
与备受尊敬的阿希什·普拉丹医生 （Ashish Pradhan) 进行对话。
Today we're taking this exploration even deeper.
今天，我们将更深入地探索。
So get ready for another thought-provoking conversation
准备好迎接另一场 发人深省的对话吧，
as we continue to bridge the worlds of science and spirituality.
我们将继续搭建科学与灵性世界 之间的桥梁。
Welcome, Dr. Pradhan.
欢迎您，普拉丹医生。
Thank you.
谢谢。
Thank you for the kind words, Monikaji.
谢谢您的美言，莫妮卡女士。
Happy to be back.
很高兴能回来。
We definitely look forward to learning a lot with you in this yet another episode.
我们非常期待在这一集中 能与您一起学到很多东西。
So, Dr. Pradhan, like I said, in our previous episode,
普拉丹医生，正如我所说， 在上一集中，
we delved into the intricate workings of the human nervous system,
我们深入探讨了 人类神经系统、自主神经系统，
the autonomic nervous system,
它们错综复杂的运作方式，
and their connections to our spiritual experiences.
以及它们与我们灵性体验的联系。
And you also distinguished between the parasympathetic, the sympathetic,
您还区分了副交感神经 和交感神经，
and explained how they interact to maintain balance,
并解释了它们如何相互作用， 以维持平衡
regulate essential functions.
及调节人体基本功能。
Today we would like to know how the autonomic nervous system intertwines
今天我们想知道 自主神经系统是如何
with the concept of the human subtle system that you briefly mentioned,
与您提到的人类精微系统概念 交织在一起的，
and how they influence our spiritual well-being?
以及它们如何影响 我们的灵性福祉？
Sure.
当然。
Let's get started right away.
我们马上开始吧。
It's a slightly complex topic.
这是一个稍微复杂的话题。
We'll try to understand this as best as we can.
我们会尽力了解这个它。
At the very outset, I would like to once again say
首先，我想重申，
that whatever we discuss in response to your questions,
我在回应你的问题时 所讨论的内容，
a lot of that knowledge comes from the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi,
其中许多知识都来自 锡吕·玛塔吉·涅玛拉·德维的教导，
the founder of Sahaja Yoga meditation,
她是霎哈嘉瑜伽冥想的创始人，
and intertwined, of course,
当然，也与我们对人类解剖学 和生理学
with what we know about human anatomy and physiology.
所知的知识交织在一起。
So let's get started.
那我们开始吧。
Before we try to understand how the autonomic nervous system and the subtle system
在我们尝试理解自主神经系统 和精微系统
sort of are correlated or interact, let's take a step back
是如何互动或起关联之前， 让我们先退一步，
and see what constitutes the subtle system.
看看什么构成 精微系统。
And from there we can proceed towards our understanding of the autonomic nervous system.
从那里，我们可以朝着 我们对自主神经系统的理解迈进。
The so-called human subtle system, as you'll see in the animation,
你会在动画中看到， 所谓的人类精微系统
comprises nadis.
是由“Nadis”（经脉）组成。
Nadis are — it's a Sanskrit word — and it can have multiple meanings.
“Nadi”是一个梵文字， 它可以有多种含义。
It can mean nerves, it can mean channels, it can mean tubes, it can mean blood vessels,
它可以指神经、管道、管状物、血管，
it can mean lymphatics, it can mean a whole host of things.
也可以指淋巴管， 它可以指代很多东西。
It's almost like one word, or like a noun for a collective,
它几乎就像一个词， 或一个集合名词，
for a whole host of individual things within the body.
用来指代身体内 所有各种各样的独立事物。
This system was described in detail
帕坦伽利（Patanjali）在 《瑜伽经》（Yoga Sutra) 中
by the Yoga Sutras of Patanjali.
详细描述了这个系统。
This is a very ancient Sanskrit text, and what you have in those texts
这是一部非常古老的梵文典籍， 这部典籍描述了
is a description of this subtle anatomy
人类系统内或人体内的
or physiology within the human body,
这种精微的解剖结构
within the human system.
或生理机能。
What the subtle system is actually, if we step even one step further
精微系统实际上是什么？ 如果我们再进一步看
or kind of step behind,
或者说退后一步看，
is actually a reflection within us of the macrocosm.
它实际上是宏观世界 在我们内在的反映。
So, what do we mean?
这是什么意思呢？
What we have within us is the microcosm.
我们内在拥有的是微观世界。
What exists outside of us, is the macrocosm.
存在于我们之外的， 是宏观世界。
And within the macrocosm, if we look at how things function,
在宏观世界里，如果我们观察 事物的运作方式，
there is a system of balance: light and dark, heavy and light,
它存在一个平衡的系统： 光明与黑暗，重与轻，
dry and wet, fire and ice.
干燥与湿润，火与冰。
So, those are naturally occurring phenomena that are present in nature.
这些都是自然界中 存在的自然现象。
It has also been described—let's say, what we spiritually or metaphorically refer to
它也被描述为——比如说，我们 在灵性上或比喻上称之为
as yin and yang.
阴和阳。
Just as there is daylight, there is night; there is the sun, there is the moon;
正如白天与黑夜； 有太阳，就有月亮；
you have high tide, you have low tide, so on and so forth.
有涨潮，就有退潮， 诸如此类。
You have summer and spring; you have fall and winter.
有夏天和春天； 也有秋天和冬天。
So, in nature we have a balance, and systems which, if overactive,
所以，在自然界中我们有一个平衡， 以及一些系统，它们如果过度活跃，
can trigger an imbalance.
就会引发不平衡。
In other words, if we have too much heat, that isn't good for the system;
换言之，如果我们有太多的热量， 那对系统是不好的；
if it's too cold, it isn't good for the system in general.
如果太冷， 对整个系统来说也是不好的。
So, ecology, or ecosystems or the universal constants that we see around us
所以生态学，或生态系统 或我们周围看到的宇宙常数，
is a very good way to begin to get an understanding
是开始理解人类精微系统
of what the human subtle system is about.
的一个很好的方式。
To slowly start coming
现在慢慢地开始
into the details and trying to answer the question.
进入细节，并尝试 回答这个问题。
As the human being evolved, or as the Homo sapiens evolved
随着人类的进化， 或者说智人（Homo Sapiens）的进化，
as we discussed the last time, the nervous system was an adaptation
正如我们上次讨论的， 神经系统是一种
to evolutionary pressures, and those evolutionary pressures
应对进化压力的适应结果， 而那些进化压力
engendered two broad systems of phenomenon
产生了​​两大类的现象系统，
from a Darwinian point of view.
从达尔文主义（Darwinism）的角度来看。
The first one was the fight or the flight response.
第一个是战斗或逃跑反应。
The fight or flight response comes into play
战斗或逃跑反应 在何时发挥作用？
if there is a threat to the organism in the environment,
当环境中存在对生物体 的威胁时，
and then it leads to what Darwin called natural selection,
它会导致达尔文所说的 自然选择（natural selection)，
or it brings down pressure upon the system or upon the species to take
或者说它给系统 或物种带来了压力，
or to adapt such characteristics that allows it to thrive in the environment.
迫使它采取或适应那些 能让它在环境中茁壮成长的特征。
So either it can overcome the danger,
一条小鱼可能会被一条更大的鱼吞食，
a smaller fish could be gobbled
所以它要么可以克服危险，
by a bigger fish, so maybe it needs to develop more sensory organs, faster fins, faster reflexes.
要么可能需要发展出 更多的感觉器官、更快的鱼鳍、更快的反应。
Similarly, a gazelle on the Serengeti plains needs to develop responses
同样的，塞伦盖蒂平原上的一只瞪羚 需要发展出反应能力，
to run away from the lion that might pursue it.
以逃离可能追捕它的狮子。
So, those are flight or flight responses
所以这些是战斗或逃跑反应，
that are part of the evolutionary mechanism.
它们是进化机制的一部分。
So, the subtle system comprises two aspects to it.
精微系统包含两个方面。
One is a passive aspect, and the other is an active aspect.
一个是被动的方面， 另一个是积极的方面。
So, we see that even in the cosmos around us, things are dynamic,
因此我们看到，即使在周围的宇宙中， 有时事物是动态的，
and sometimes they are passive,
有时它们又是被动的，
both at the same time, and it's not a contradiction.
两者同时存在， 而且这并不矛盾。
The whole system through immutable laws, and we call them the laws of divinity,
整个系统通过永恒不变的法则， 我们称之为神圣的法则，
the laws of the Almighty, call it what you will, to each his own,
全能者的法则， 你可以随便怎么称呼，各随其好，
but the system works in a state of balance.
但这个系统是在 一种平衡状态下运作的。
So, likewise, in the human body, now to start coming back to the point,
我们现在回到正题。 同样的在人体中，
we have a system which is the passive system;
我们有一个被动的系统；
we have a system which is the active system.
我们也有一个动态的系统。
On the left side, so to speak,
可以这么说，
we call it the moon channel, or we call it the Ida Nadi;
在左侧，我们称之为月亮脉， 或者叫它为左脉（Ida Nadi）；
on the right side, we call it the sun channel, or we call it the Pingala Nadi.
在右侧，我们称之为太阳脉， 或者叫它为右脉（Pingala Nadi）。
The left side, or the moon channel, is more passive; it allows passivity,
左侧或月亮脉， 更具被动性；它容许被动，
but passivity that doesn't mean sloth or lethargy.
但被动并不意味着 懒惰或昏沉。
It can get into it if it is overactive.
如果它过度活跃，就可能陷入那种状态。
Similarly, on the right side, we have the ability to act,
同样的，在右侧，我们有行动的能力，
to bring our desires into fruition, but again, if that becomes overactive,
去实现我们的愿望， 但同样的，如果它变得过度活跃，
that becomes a problem too.
那也会成为问题。
We can become: aggressive, overthinking, overplanning, that sort of a thing.
我们可能变得：好斗、过度思考、 过度计划，诸如此类。
So, within the human body, the subtle system has these two components; they are called Nadis,
所以在人体内部，精微系统有这两个 组成部分；它们被称为经脉（Nadis），
and that's how it functions.
系统就是这样运作的。
Now, back to, once again, to the evolutionary component.
现在再回到进化的部分。
Within the evolutionary system, as we said, there is a flight or fight pressures,
在进化系统中，正如我们所说， 存在着逃跑或战斗的压力，
but there is also the need to evolve.
但也存在着进化的需要。
The need to evolve into a higher state, both at a physical,
向更高状态进化的需要， 无论是在身体上，
but as well as at a cognitive, or at a nervous system level, or at a neural level.
还是在认知上， 或是在神经系统层面， 或是在神经元层面。
And that is how we described during the last session
这就是我们在上次会谈中 所描述的
how the brain evolved in response to some of these pressures.
大脑是如何响应这些压力 而进化的。
So, likewise, in the subtle system, there is a third component,
同样的，在精微系统中， 还有第三个部分，
the so-called Sushumna Nadi, and that is a kind of power
所谓的 Sushumna Nadi（中脉）， 那是一种力量，
that allows evolution to proceed.
它允许进化继续进行。
We know how these changes are brought about through genetic changes that are passed
我们知道这些变化是如何带来的， 透过基因的改变，
onto the offspring from the parent that has allowed it to survive.
从亲代传给后代，让它得以生存。
These are the three components of the subtle system.
这就是精微系统的 三个组成部分。
On the left side, the passive side, the so-called Ida Nadi;
在左侧，是被动的一侧， 所谓的左脉（Ida Nadi）；
on the right side, the so-called sun channel, the active side or the Pingala Nadi;
在右侧，所谓的太阳脉， 是主动的一侧或右脉（Pingala Nadi）；
and in the center, we have a power
在中央，我们拥有一种力量，
that allows evolution but, evolution in a spiritual sense.
它允许进化，但是 是灵性意义上的进化。
The microcosm is reflected in the macrocosm, and now we come to the autonomic nervous system.
微观世界反映在宏观世界中， 现在我们来看看自主神经系统。
The autonomic nervous system also has its two components.
自主神经系统 也有它的两个组成部分。
One is the sympathetic nervous system; the other is the parasympathetic nervous system.
一个是交感神经系统； 另一个是副交感神经系统。
The sympathetic nervous system governs your flight or fight responses.
交感神经系统 支配着你的战斗或逃跑反应。
For example, a human being sees a danger,
例如，一个人看到危险，
either he or she wants to fight
他要么就想战斗，
or to run away from it.
不然就想逃离它。
That triggers your heart rate to either pump faster, maybe run away from the danger.
这会触发你的心率， 使它跳得更快， 好让你逃离危险。
So that's one.
这是一点。
The other is the evolutionary, or the parasympathetic nervous system.
另一个是进化的， 或者说是副交感神经系统。
The parasympathetic nervous system is your rest-and-digest system.
副交感神经系统 是你的“休息与消化”系统。
It allows the individual to repose, to relax, and to nourish.
它让个体得以休憩、放松和滋养。
The left and the right, the subtle systems,
精微系统的左侧和右侧，
or the sympathetic systems, are something that are energy-expending systems.
或者说交感神经系统， 是消耗能量的系统。
They consume energy; they expend energy.
它们消耗能量；它们支出能量。
We either consume energy in our desires, by having desires,
通过拥有欲望， 我们要么在欲望中消耗能量，
or we consume energy bringing those desires into action.
要么将这些欲望 付诸行动时消耗能量。
The parasympathetic nervous system allows us to rest and to nourish ourselves,
副交感神经系统让我们 休息和滋养自己，
and in that way, through mechanisms that we have not yet biologically elucidated,
并且通过（我们尚未 在生物学上阐明的）机制，
allow us to evolve.
让我们得以进化。
I'll stop there.
我就讲到这里。
I hope that that kind of answers the question, but I'm happy to take more questions
我希望这在一定程度上回答了你的问题， 但如果解释得不够充分，
if that did not fully explain it.
我很乐意回答更多问题。
Thanks, Dr. Ashish, for that explanation. And as we continue to zoom
谢谢阿希什医生的解释。 在我们继续深入
into the subtle system, after having understood a bit about
精微系统的同时， 理解了这些能量通道
these energy channels or these Nadis, we would like to understand from you
或经脉之后， 我们想请教您
a little bit about the plexus now.
关于神经丛（plexus）的一些知识。
So, how is a plexus formed?
例如一个神经丛是如何形成的？
What role do plexuses play in the functioning of the human body?
神经丛在人体功能中 扮演着什么角色？
Things of that nature, if you can explain to the audiences.
诸如此类的问题， 请您向观众解释一下。
Sure.
当然。
So, a plexus is derived from the Latin word,
Plexus（神经丛）这个词 源自拉丁语，
and it means a braid,
意思是“编织物”或“辫子”，
like a braid of hair, for example, like women who have hair, longer hair,
比如头发的辫子，举个例子， 像女性留长发，
or even men or women, if you tie that in a braid, that's the word, that's the origin of it.
或者男性或女性，如果你把头发扎成辫子， 就是这个词，这是它的起源。
That's how it looks.
它看起来就是那样的。
Why is it called a plexus?
为什么它被称为神经丛？
We saw last time that the central nervous system consists of the brain and the spinal cord,
我们上次看到，中枢神经系统 由大脑和脊髓组成，
and through the spinal cord which passes through the vertebral column,
而脊髓穿过椎骨，
you have nerves that come out of the vertebra from the sides.
神经从椎骨的两侧发出。
When the nerves come out from the vertebra, they come together
当神经从椎骨中出来时， 它们从不同的部位
from different parts, and the plexus is like, if you open the electrical box
汇集在一起，神经丛就像是： 如果你打开家里的电箱，
in your house, you see a bunch of wires coming together.
你会看到一堆电线 汇集在一起。
So, a plexus is like nature's way of organizing the nerves.
所以，神经丛就像是大自然 组织神经的方式。
The nerves that come out, and these nerves, as we know, go further out,
这些神经伸出之后， 会进一步延伸，
and they enter the various organs of the body.
进入身体的各个器官，
So, whether it is the heart, whether it is the lungs,
无论是心脏，还是肺部，
whether it is the stomach, the pancreas, the liver.
无论是胃、胰脏还是肝脏，
And also, of course, the skeletal musculature.
当然，还有骨骼肌系统。
So, these nerves, when they come out, they bunch together,
所以这些神经出来时， 它们会聚集在一起，
they come together, and that is what is called a plexus.
汇合在一起， 这就是所谓的神经丛。
A plexus is, from a Sahaj point of view,
从霎哈嘉瑜伽的观点来看， 神经丛是我们所说的
the gross manifestation of what we call energy centers or chakras within the body.
体内能量中心或脉轮（chakras) 的物质表现。
The Yoga Sutras have described seven principal energy centers.
《瑜伽经》描述了 七个主要的能量中心。
There are multiple other centers as well, but there are seven energy centers
还有许多其他的中心， 但有七个主要的能量中心，
that start from something that is below our vertebral column,
从我们脊椎下方 的某个地方开始，
right up the way, right into the crown of our head.
一路向上， 直到头顶冠部。
The hypothesis is that the energy center itself exists
这个假设是， 能量中心本身存在于
at a very, very subtle level within the human body.
人体内一个非常、非常精微的 层面。
The energy center, or the chakra, cannot actually be seen
这个能量中心，或者说轮穴， 实际上是无法通过
through any current means of diagnostic techniques,
任何现有的诊断技术看到的，
for example, MRI scans or functional MRI scans or CT scans.
例如，MRI 扫描、 功能性 MRI 扫描或 CT 扫描。
You cannot put something in and try to see it functionally,
你无法放入什么东西 来看它的功能，
nor can you dissect the body at a level where you see it,
也无法在解剖层面看到它，
because these energy centers function or exist at the plane of energy.
因为这些能量中心都在 能量层面上运作或存在。
It is not a matter per se; it is energy.
它本身不是物质；它是能量。
And these energy centers, at specific parts of the human body,
而在人体的特定部位， 这些能量中心
govern the functioning of these nerve centers we call plexuses.
支配着这些我们称为神经丛 的神经中心的运作。
The energy flow is from the energy center to the plexus,
能量的流动是从能量中心 到神经丛，
and from the plexus, it goes through the nerves into the organs.
然后从神经丛，通过神经 进入各个器官。
That is how the energy center - the chakra - governs the functioning
这就是能量中心或轮穴 如何支配
of the human body in the autonomic nervous system.
人体自主神经系统 的运作方式。
That’s essentially the schema.
这基本上就是模式。
So, you have the energy center that has the energy
所以，你有能量中心， 它拥有能量，
that, quote-unquote, controls— I have to use hand quotes here—
它“控制”着—— 我这里必须用手势打引号——
because there is no real neurotransmitter-y system, as we discussed last time.
因为没有真正的神经递质-- 系统，就像我们上次讨论过的。
There is no acetylcholine, there is no adrenaline,
没有乙酰胆碱（acetylcholine）， 没有肾上腺素（adrenaline），
there is no dopamine or serotonin that does it.
没有多巴胺（dopamine） 或血清素 (serotonin) 来做这件事。
But through ways that we have not yet elucidated, but you can feel it through your awareness
但是通过我们尚未阐明的方式， 一旦你练习这种冥想形式，
once you practice this form of meditation, that the energy flows
你可以通过你的觉知 感觉到能量的流动——
from the energy center to the plexus, from the plexus to the organ,
从能量中心到神经丛， 从神经丛到器官，
and that is how the chakra, plexus, organ system functions to maintain, once again,
这就是轮穴、神经丛、器官系统 如何维持身体平衡及
the balance in the body, the internal ecosystem of the body.
体内生态系统的运作方法。
That is how the nadis and the chakras come together.
这就是经脉（Nadis） 和轮穴（Chakras）如何结合的方式。
It is very important to remember, as we go on our journey
在继续旅程时， 我们会在以后的节目中讨论这一点：
and we discuss this in future episodes, that we should avoid the trap
我们应该避免掉进 现代医学所陷入的陷阱，
that modern medicine has fallen into, which is to look at individual components
就是只看单个组成部分
and then try to make a sense of the whole.
然后试图理解整体。
To understand the human spiritual system or the subtle system, one needs to take, in fact,
若要理解人类的灵性系统 或精微系统，实际上需要采取
the directly opposite approach, which is a holistic approach,
完全相反的方法，即一种 整体的方法（holistic approach)。
to start from understanding that the system functions in an integrated fashion,
还原方法（reductive approach) 则是从了解系统
and to try to break it down
以整合的方式运作开始，
into its components is a reductive approach.
并尝试将系统拆解为其组成部分。
But, at the same time, it does help to understand a little bit,
这个方法确实有助于 我们理解一些东西，
but that is how it functions.
但它就是这样运作的。
So, even if one chakra controls, maybe in theory, one plexus,
所以，即使一个轮穴在理论上 控制着一个神经丛，
in reality, it probably controls many, many more plexuses
在现实中，它可能控制着 许多更多的神经丛，
and functions in ways that are very complex, that human understanding still hasn't
并以非常复杂的方式运作。 人类对此的理解
been able to pattern.
至今还未能弄明白。
I will stop there.
我就讲到这里。
I hope that provides some perspective of why the plexus is so important to understand
我希望我所提供的这些观点， 能让我们明白为什么神经丛
within the broader concept of human spirituality.
对了解人类灵性的广泛概念 是如此重要。
Thanks, Dr. Ashish, for that understanding, because all along I always thought
谢谢阿希什医生的理解， 因为我一直以为
that chakra, energy center, and plexus are all the same things,
轮穴、能量中心和神经丛 都是同样的东西，
and I know we use these terms without knowing so much about them,
我知道我们使用这些术语时 对它们了解不多，
but thanks for explaining that.
但谢谢您的解释。
If you can talk to us
您能谈谈轮穴和神经丛之间
about the hypothesis that underlies the relationship
的关系的假设吗？
between a chakra and a plexus, and why is it important for us to understand that?
以及为何理解这一点很重要？
Excellent.
非常好。
So, the chakra is, from a Sahaj point of view,
从霎哈嘉的角度来看， 轮穴（Chakra）是
the seat of divine power.
是神圣力量的所在。
It expresses itself as pure love, and each of these energy centers, or chakras,
它表现为纯粹的爱， 而每一个能量中心或轮穴
manifest different qualities.
都显现出不同的品质。
And it is through the energy center - that is, the chakra -
正是通过能量中心或轮穴，
that the energy transmitted to the plexus governs the functioning
能量被传输到神经丛， 从而支配着
of that particular organ system or organs within the remit of that plexus.
该神经丛掌管的特定器官系统 或器官的功能。
So, as we will see as we move along, there are specific plexuses
当我们继续探讨时， 我们会看到有特定的神经丛
that look after specific organs.
照管特定的器官。
The reason why this is important
这一点之所以重要
is to understand both the physiology and the pathology.
是为了理解生理和病理。
The physiology is very simple, as we just expressed.
生理学方面容易理解， 正如我们所表述的。
Energy transmitted to the plexus and therefore the functioning of the organ system.
能量传输到神经丛， 从而影响器官系统的功能。
Equally important, if the energy center is overused,
一样重要的是， 当能量中心被过度使用之时。
there is a finite amount of energy
当一个人出生时，
that is present at each of the individual chakra levels
每个独立的轮穴层面
when an individual takes birth.
都存在着有限的能量。
And throughout our life, we keep on expending that energy that we are born with,
在我们的一生中，我们不断消耗 与生俱来的能量，
unless and until you get into a state we call self-realization,
除非并且直到你进入一种 我们称之为自觉的状态，
and then that energy can be replenished.
然后那份能量才能得到补充。
But for most individuals, from the time of their birth
但对大多数人来说， 从他们出生那一刻起，
till they pass on, is a limited amount of energy.
直到他们去世， 能量是有限的。
If that energy is not used in a wise and an optimal manner,
如果那份能量没有被 明智且最佳地使用，
then it places strain on that chakra.
那么它就会给那个轮穴带来压力。
That strain is then reflected at the level of the plexus
这种压力接着会反映 在神经丛的层面上，
because there is an imbalance.
因为出现了不平衡。
The key to understanding everything is the balance of this ecosystem.
理解一切的关键 是这个生态系统的平衡。
And if that plexus gets into a state of imbalance, quote-unquote.
如果那个神经丛进入了 “失衡”的状态，
Medicine doesn't easily explain this,
这一点医学并不容易解释，
but at the spiritual level, we can explain it
但在灵性层面上， 我们可以通过我们在霎哈嘉瑜伽中
through our growth in our self-awareness through Sahaj.
自我觉知的成长，去解释它。
If the plexus gets imbalanced, then the organ systems it governs
如果神经丛失衡， 那么它所支配的器官系统
get imbalanced as well.
也会失衡。
Which - in other words - is what we mean by imbalance?
我们说的失衡是什么意思？
Imbalance implies the beginning of a pathological state,
失衡意味着病理状态的开始，
which may or may not be easily detectable, but it starts at a very subtle level,
它可能不容易被检测到， 但它始于非常精微的层面，
and then over a period of time, it manifests as gross pathology.
然后经过一段时间， 它会表现为明显的病理。
And that is why it is important to understand the governance structure
这就是为什么理解 这个治理结构很重要:
from the energy center, that is the chakra, to the plexus, to the organ system.
从能量中心，即轮穴， 到神经丛，再到器官系统。
Doctor, from what you mentioned, it seems like there has to be a wise use
医生，根据您所提到的， 似乎有必要明智地使用
of the finite energy that we are born with.
我们与生俱来的有限能量。
If you can help us understand what does it mean to use that energy wisely
您能帮助我们理解 明智地使用能量是什么意思吗？
or discreetly so that we don't get our chakras out of balance?
或者说谨慎地使用，这样我们就不会让 我们的轮穴失衡？
Let's take an example of a heart chakra,
让我们以心轮为例，
the one that governs the cardiac plexus and our cardiovascular system,
它支配着心神经丛 和我们的心血管系统，
but basically the cardiac system.
但基本上是心脏系统。
For example, if we overwork, if we overstrain ourselves,
例如，如果我们过度工作， 如果我们过度劳累自己，
we know that we are pursuing something, maybe it's a career opportunity,
我们知道自己正在追求某样东西， 也许是一个职业机会，
we want to work, and everybody wants to get ahead in life, and that's okay.
我们想要工作，每个人都想 在生活中取得进步，这不是问题。
The question is, is your ambition, is your drive putting you in a place
问题是，你的雄心、 你的动力是否让你实际感受到
where you can actually feel that you are under stress,
自己处于压力之下，
and that stress, at some point,
而那种压力在某个时刻，
is manifesting in the form of essential hypertension.
正表现为自发性高血压。
Your systolic is going up, your diastolic is going up,
你的收缩压(systolic pressure) 在上升， 你的舒张压(diastolic pressure) 也在上升，
at a certain age or whatever the case may be; then knowingly doing it,
在某个年龄，或者不管情况如何； 那么明知故犯地做下去，
or continuing to do it, is being unwise about it,
或者继续这样做， 就是不明智的，
because now we should know. Most people don't have knowledge
因为现在我们应该知道了。 大多数人没有轮穴的知识，
about the chakras, but they do understand blood pressure or hypertension—
但他们确实理解血压或高血压——
because, potentially, it's a silent thing. But if you get the symptoms,
因为它可能是一种无声的疾病。 但如果你出现了症状，
and if you are diagnosed with it, that's different.
并且你被诊断出患有此病， 那就不一样了。
So, this is what we mean by being wise about it: that whatever your drives in life,
所以，这就是我们所说的明智行事： 无论你在生活中有何动力，
whatever your desires, wisdom, which is, again, an innate quality
无论你有何欲望， 智慧必须体现在我们的欲望和行动中
that comes to us from the first energy center, which we shall be talking about shortly,
否则系统就会失衡。
needs to manifest itself in both our desires as well as our actions,
智慧是一种与生俱来的品质，
because otherwise the system goes out of that.
它来自第一个能量中心， 我们稍后会谈到。
The energy center for that particular organ, or for that particular system,
那个特定器官 或那个特定系统的能量中心，
can start manifesting in ways that we now describe as, maybe, diseases
可能会开始表现为疾病 或人体失调，
or disorders of the human body.
如我们现在所描述的。
It is said that we often lead our lives in ignorance and, unknowingly or knowingly,
据说我们常常有意或无意地 在无知中生活，
put so much demand on our energy centers to the extent that we are creating
对我们的能量中心造成了负荷, 以至于我们正为自己制造
pathological conditions for us, like you explained.
病理状况， 如你所解释的一样。
Doctor, we'd like to understand if modern medicine historically has studied
医生，我们想了解一下 现代医学在历史上是否研究过
or tried to study any connection between the autonomic nervous system
或者试图研究过自主神经系统
and the subtle system.
和精微系统之间的任何联系。
That's a great question, Monikaji.
这是个很好的问题，莫妮卡女士。
Modern medicine has not really tried,
现代医学 并没有真正尝试过，
though if we look at the Hippocratic tradition,
虽然我们如果回顾 希波克拉底的传统， （Hippocratic tradition）
it certainly tried in the past, particularly during the time of Hippocrates, to make that linkage.
医学在过去时代，特别是在 希波克拉底（Hippocrates) 的时代, 肯定尝试过去建立那种联系。
For example, Hippocrates was known to use methods that would bring the systems into balance.
例如，希波克拉底以使用能够 恢复系统平衡的方法而闻名。
But Galen, who succeeded Hippocrates for about 1500 years,
但继希波克拉底之后的盖伦（Galen）， 在大约1500年的时间里，
his theory of humors (H-U-M-O-R, as in humours),
他的体液学说（Humor Theory）
looked at trying to balance out the systems
着眼于试图平衡系统，
between hot and cold,
在冷与热之间，
like the subtle system does, and then look at it from that point of view.
就像精微系统所做的那样， 然后从那个角度来看待它。
So, medicine had some, maybe in the distant past,
所以，遥远过去的医学 可能理解到了
an understanding of the need to balance these elements within us.
平衡我们内在这些元素的必要性。
So, that was one, and Galen's theory of humours dominated medicine till about the Renaissance
所以，这一方面，盖伦的体液学说 主导了医学，直到文艺复兴时期，
and the arrival of the scientific method, the dissection of the human body,
以及科学方法的到来、 人体解剖学的发展、
the understanding of physiologic mechanisms, and then we lost it.
对生理机制的理解， 然后我们就失去了它。
So, modern medicine doesn't really investigate it that much.
所以，现代医学并没有真正 深入研究它。
In Ayurveda, it's probably become closest to bridging that gap
阿育吠陀或许是最接近于 弥合精微系统
between the subtle system and the autonomic nervous system,
与自主神经系统之间鸿沟的方法,
particularly through the tridosha theory, which is the kapha-pitta-vata theory,
特别是通过“三元”(Tridosha) 理论， 即卡法－皮塔－瓦塔（Kapha–Pitta–Vata）理论，
which looks at the body as a composition of five elements:
它将身体视为 五种元素的组合：
earth, fire, water, ether, and air.
土、火、水、以太和空气。
So, it is through the tridosha theory— this tripartite theory—
正是通过这个三元理论——
that we try to understand the relationship between the subtle system and the gross system,
我们试图理解精微系统与粗糙（物质）系统 之间的关系，
and Ayurveda tries to use these elements to bring the body to a state of balance.
而阿育吠陀试图利用这些元素 来使身体达到平衡状态。
But that's as far as medical systems go.
但就医学体系而言，也就到此为止了。
There are other systems of medicine; the Chinese system tries to balance
还有其他的医学体系； 中医体系
the yin and yang part of it.
试图平衡阴和阳的部分。
So, medicine historically has had an understanding of it,
所以在历史上，医学曾经 对它（精微系统）有所了解，
but not to the extent that Sahaj can provide.
但没有达到像 霎哈嘉瑜伽所能提供的程度。
Now that we understand that there are these energy centers,
现在我们理解了 这些能量中心的存在，
let's begin by talking about the very first energy center.
让我们从谈论 第一个能量中心开始。
Could we understand a little bit about this and its role in human evolution
我们能了解一下这个中心 以及它在人类进化
as well as in spirituality?
和灵性中的作用吗？
The first energy center is, it would not be an overstatement to say,
我毫不夸张地说， 理解第一个能量中心，
hypercritical to understand it, because it truly is the beginning of it all.
是至关重要， 因为它确实是一切的开端。
It is called the Muladhara chakra.
它被称为根轮（Mooladhara chakra）。
It sits outside of the vertebral column, just below it.
它位于脊柱之外， 就在其下方。
It exists at an extremely subtle level.
它存在于一个极其精微的层面。
As we said, there is no way to see these energy centers,
正如我们所说，我们没有办法 看到这些能量中心，
but we can perceive them.
但我们可以感知到它们。
So that chakra, Muladhara, essentially means the primordial support.
所以那个轮穴——根轮（Muladhara）， 基本上意味着原始的支撑。
It really is the fulcrum of everything.
它确实是一切的支撑点。
Before we start to understand the Muladhara chakra,
在开始理解根轮之前，
maybe just a step back into basic physics or quantum mechanics,
我们或许可以先退一步，回到 基础物理学或量子力学，
or quantum field theory.
或者量子场论。
Why is that important?
为什么这很重要？
It's very important because, if you remember, in 2012, the CERN particle collider
这非常重要，因为如果你记得， 在2012年，欧洲核子研究中心的粒子对撞机 （CERN particle collider）
found the Higgs boson particle.
发现了希格斯玻色子 （Higgs boson particle）。
Why was that important?
为什么那很重要？
Why was the Nobel Prize awarded to the individuals who had, 40 years ago,
为什么诺贝尔奖要颁给 那些在40年前
propounded that theory?
提出那个理论的个人？
And the reason is the existence of the Higgs field,
原因在于希格斯场 的存在。
which is supposed to permeate all known universes.
它被认为弥漫于 所有已知的宇宙。
And what the Higgs boson proved was that energy somehow imparts properties
而希格斯玻色子证明的是， 能量以某种方式
to electromagnetic particles, or at that quantum level,
将其特性赋予了电磁粒子， 或在那个量子层面上，
in that quantum state, that gives them mass.
在那个量子状态下， 赋予了它们质量。
Mass, in turn, produces gravity.
而质量又产生了重力（gravity）。
What is gravity?
重力是什么？
It's the curvature of space-time.
它是时空的曲率。
So, whatever mass you have, it leads to that part of gravity,
所以，无论你拥有多少质量， 它都会导致那部分重力，
and that is a constant.
而那是一个常数（constant）。
Newton showed us that there is a constant in terms of gravity.
牛顿向我们展示了 重力方面有一个常数。
Why is that important?
为什么这很重要？
This is important to know that energy preceded the creation of matter,
了解这一点很重要， 即能量先于物质的创造，
and that helps us to understand our subtle system and also our chakras.
这有助于我们理解 我们的精微系统以及我们的轮穴。
The Muladhara chakra, or the first energy center, represents
根轮或第一个能量中心，代表着
that first primordial step after the Big Bang, or around that time, or just following that,
宇宙大爆炸后的第一个原始步骤， 或在那段时间，或紧随其后，
as this heat was released, and then that heat started slowly,
当这股热量被释放， 然后这股热量慢慢地，
as the system started coalescing,
随着系统开始凝聚，
leading to the formation of the big stars. And within the cores of these big stars,
导致了大恒星的形成。 而在这些大恒星的核心内部，
you had fusion reactions where hydrogen and helium nuclei
发生了核聚变反应， 氢和氦的原子核
started coming together, and elements were formed.
开始结合在一起， 元素就形成了。
And a key element was carbon.
一个关键元素是碳。
And carbon, as we know, is tetravalent.
我们知道碳是四价的。
It has four valencies, and it is the basic molecule
它有四个价键， 它是形成
that leads to formation of organic compounds.
有机化合物的基本分子。
And the human being, or everything that we see around us,
而人类 或者我们周围看到的一切，
animals, plants, whatever,
动物、植物，等等，
is a product of that organic chemistry.
都是那有机化学的产物。
So this element, carbon, which has four valencies,
所以碳这个元素， 它有四个价键，
is also interestingly represented in some ways as the swastika,
在某种程度上也有趣地被 万字符号（Swastika）所代表，
which is a very traditional ancient symbol.
那是一个非常传统古老的符号。
Unfortunately, in the last century, it got a very bad reputation,
不幸的是，在上个世纪， 它却招来了坏名声，
but it has nothing to do with it.
但它与纳粹毫无关系。
It has been recognized as a symbol of auspiciousness and purity
它一直被认为是吉祥 和纯洁的象征，
and everything that goes with it.
以及与之相关的一切。
So, that is how it starts.
就是这样开始的。
So, this is the Muladhara chakra.
这就是根轮。
The Muladhara chakra is the fulcrum, literally the support of the entire system,
根轮是支点， 名副其实是整个系统的支撑，
and it is governed by an aspect of divinity whose manifestation is primordial innocence.
它由一个神圣的面向所支配， 其显现是原始的纯真。
So, once again, to recap, you have energy,
所以再总结一下： 你有能量，
that is the primordial energy that somehow imparted its properties
那是原始的能量， 它以某种方式将其特性赋予了
to electromagnetic particles that created mass, and that mass led to gravity.
电磁粒子， 从而创造了质量，而那质量导致了重力。
And without gravity, we would not have existed,
没有重力， 我们就不会存在，
because otherwise we would have just been,
因为否则我们就会
like electrons spinning forever at the speed of light.
像电子一样以光速 永远旋转。
And that gravity is also kept at a very specific constant,
而那重力也保持在 一个非常特定的常数，
because if that constant were to be a little less or a little more
因为如果那个常数 稍微小一点或大一点，
we would have just collapsed together into
我们就会坍缩在一起，
a hyperdense kind of matter that would be impossible to define;
成为一种超高密度的物质， 那将是无法定义的；
or if it had been less, we would have just been flying into space.
或者如果它更小， 我们就会直接飞向太空。
Muladhara chakra is very important because it represents that primordial purity
根轮非常重要， 因为它代表了那创造我们的力量 的原始纯洁，
of the power that created us, and at a gross level, it is represented
在物质层面上，
by the pelvic plexus.
它由盆腔神经丛(pelvic plexus) 所代表。
The pelvic plexus is formed by nerves that come out of the sacrum bone
盆腔神经丛是由骶骨
and as well as the last parts of the lumbar vertebra.
和腰椎最后部分​​的神经所组成。
They come together, they exist on both sides, and the pelvic plexus innervates
它们汇集在一起，存在于两侧， 而盆腔神经丛在人体内，
the excretory organs as well as the reproductive organs
无论男或女，都支配着
in the human body, in males as well as females,
排泄器官以及生殖器官，
as shown in the animation.
有如动画所示。
For example, the uterus or the urinary bladder,
例如，子宫或膀胱，
the excretory organs, those are the organs that are controlled —
排泄器官，这些器官 受到控制——
again, the word 'control' is used in a spiritual sense, not just in a physical sense —
“控制”这个词是在 灵性意义上使用的， 而不仅仅是物理意义上——
by the pelvic plexus.
由盆腔神经丛控制。
The pelvic plexus—there are two of them on either side of the vertebral column
盆腔神经丛—— 在脊柱两侧各有一个，
at the lower part of the body (the lower pelvis). That's why it's called the pelvic plexus,
位于身体的下部（下骨盆）。 所以它被称为盆腔神经丛，
and that's how they control these organs.
它们就是这样控制这些器官的。
But the power that controls the plexuses is represented by the Muladhara chakra.
但是控制这些神经丛的力量 是由根轮所代表的。
Before we end this question, to re-emphasize what we said
在我们结束这个问题之前， 再次强调我们
in answer to a previous question, the Muladhara chakra should not be
在回答前一个问题时所说的， 根轮不应该
looked at in a unitary fashion; it is to be seen as part of an integral system
被单一地看待； 它应被视为整体系统的一部分，
that literally sits above it, but the Muladhara chakra provides
这个系统实际上位于它之上， 但根轮提供了
the support to it all, and its main function is to provide gravity,
对这一切的支撑，而它的主要功能 是提供重力，
and through that gravity, it allows the support of the entire system.
并通过那份重力，它支撑着 整个系统。
It is an extraordinarily important energy center to be aware of.
这是一个极其重要的 需要去觉知的能量中心。
You mentioned two things: you mentioned the sacrum bone,
您提到了两件事： 您提到了骶骨（os sacrum），
and we'd like to understand why it is considered relevant in this context.
我们想了解一下 为什么它在这种背景下被认为是相关的。
You also mentioned primordial energy. Is this the same as the Kundalini energy
您还提到了原始能量。 这和我们听说过的昆达里尼能量
that we hear about, and what is this Kundalini energy,
是一样的吗？ 这个昆达里尼能量是什么？
and what role does it play in human spirituality?
它在人类灵性中扮演什么角色？
That is indeed true.
的确如此。
Once again, as we look at the graphics, we look at the animation,
再次，当我们看这些图示， 看这个动画时，
we see that at the bottom of the vertebral column
我们看到在脊柱的底部
is a triangular bone called the os sacrum.
有一块三角形的骨头 叫做骶骨（os sacrum）。
The Greeks realized that this was a very sacred place,
希腊人意识到 这是一个非常神圣的地方，
and there is no reason to know so far, as far as we know,
据我们所知，目前还找不到原因解释
why they would call it that particular bone.
他们为什么会称那块骨头为那个名字。
There are theories about it; it is said that that is amongst the last bones
关于它有各种理论； 据说那是人体中最后
to be destroyed in the human body if a body is interred or is buried.
被摧毁的骨头之一， 如果一具尸体被埋葬。
It is an extremely strong bone; it looks like the hood of a snake,
这是一块极其坚固的骨头； 它看起来像蛇的头罩，
and within this os sacrum, and this is why we believe in human spirituality,
而这就是为什么我们 在人类灵性中相信，
resides the primordial energy in three and a half coils,
这块骶骨内居住着原始的能量， 它以三圈半的盘绕状，
in the serpentine coils, and that energy is referred to in the yoga sutras
蛇形盘绕着。 那种能量在瑜伽经中
or in classical Sanskrit texts as Kundalini.
或在古典梵文典籍中被称为 昆达里尼（Kundalini）。
Kundala means coiled and it sits there in three and a half coils.
“Kundala”的意思是盘绕的， 它以三圈半的形式盘踞在那里。
Other texts refer to it as the serpent power,
其他文献称之为 蛇的力量，
or that power that resides within us.
或居住在我们内在的那种力量。
It is very interesting that ancient Greeks used to worship a god called Asclepius,
非常有趣的是古希腊人 曾经崇拜过一位叫做 阿斯克勒庇俄斯（Asclepius）的神，
and Asclepius was known to cure diseases with the use of serpent power.
而阿斯克勒庇俄斯以使用 蛇的力量治愈疾病而闻名。
So, even now, if you look at the most visible symbol of most physicians
即使现在，如果你看到 大多数医生
or medical societies you see a staff, and you see two serpents coiled around it,
或医学会最显眼的标志， 你会看到一根权杖， 上面有两条蛇盘绕着，
and that comes from the legend of Asclepius, who was believed to cure diseases
那是来自于阿斯克勒庇俄斯的传说， 他被认为能
using serpent power.
用蛇的力量治愈疾病。
So, this is this energy that resides within us; this is the energy that allows us
所以，这就是居住在我们内在的能量； 正是这种能量让我们
to raise our consciousness from a human level to a level whereby we can perceive
从人类的意识层面 提升到一个可以感知到
this existential reality that is absolute,
这种存在的、绝对的实相的层面，
that we referred to in one of our previous episodes.
我们在之前的一集中提到过。
The sympathetic nervous system has nerves
交感神经系统有神经
that permeate each part of our body, including our nerves,
渗透到我们身体的每个部分。
and when this energy is awakened within us, as it rises through the other energy centers,
当这种能量在我们内在被唤醒， 当它穿过其他能量中心上升时，
which we will talk about in subsequent episodes,
（我们将在后续几集中 讨论这些能量中心）
and it arrives and it pierces through the limbic system,
它到达并穿透边缘系统，
the fontanel area in that part of the brain, it allows us to feel that energy around us
即大脑的囟门区域， 它让我们能感觉到我们周围的能量，
that we otherwise cannot at a sensory level, and that is very important.
而这是我们在感官层面上 通常无法感觉到的。 这一点非常重要。
Biologically, it's interesting that it may not be
从生物学角度看，有趣的是 它可能不是
the Kundalini energy per se, but the Kundalini energy —
昆达里尼能量本身， 但昆达里尼能量
the fact that it allows an evolution — bears an interesting parallel
能促进进化的事实—— 与DNA分子的双螺旋结构
to the double helical structure of the DNA molecule.
有着有趣的相似之处。
The DNA molecule, which exists within every cell and is the fundamental unit
DNA分子存在于每一个细胞中， 是所有生物体的
of all living organisms in every cell, consists of two strands
每个细胞中的基本单位， 是由两条链组成的，
that spiral around each other.
它们相互螺旋缠绕。
One goes up, one goes down, and it contains the genetic code within itself,
一条向上，一条向下， 它自身包含了遗传密码，
and the reason why, as the founder of Sahaja, Shri Mataji, once explained, it is helical
而正如霎哈嘉瑜伽的创始人， 锡吕·玛塔吉曾经解释的， 它之所以是螺旋形的，
is because a helical movement allows you, if you move it, to arrive at a higher plane.
是因为螺旋运动允许你， 如果你移动它， 到达一个更高的层面。
Circular movement allows you to only come back to the starting point,
圆周运动只允许你 回到起点，
but a helical movement allows you to rise up.
但螺旋运动让你能够上升。
That's why you have a spiral staircase.
这就是为什么有螺旋楼梯。
So, in a kind of analogous fashion, the Kundalini energy allows us,
所以以类比的方式， 当它解开盘绕并上升时，
when it uncoils and as it rises, to raise our consciousness.
昆达里尼能量让我们 提升我们的意识。
This is present in every human being, and it is also called the mother energy.
这存在于每一个人之中， 它也被称为母亲的能量。
It is your individual mother because this is the energy that knows best
它是你个人的母亲， 因为这种能量最了解
what is good for you, what is best for you. And it is a female energy
什么对你最好，什么最适合你。 这是一种雌性能量，
that resides within each one of us, dormant in the sacrum.
它潜伏在我们每个人的内在， 沉睡在荐骨中。
And it is the awakening of this energy
而正是这种能量的唤醒，
which is the ultimate object of all yoga practices.
是所有瑜伽练习的 最终目标。
In fact, yoga is defined as the awakening of this energy and its piercing
事实上，瑜伽被定义为这种能量的 唤醒，以及它穿透
through the fontanel area, and the awakening of the limbic system.
囟门区域， 以及边缘系统的觉醒。
So, that's the Kundalini energy, which resides in the sacrum,
所以，这就是昆达里尼能量， 它居住在荐骨中，
and which certain systems of medicine, particularly in the past, were kind of aware of.
而某些医学体系， 尤其是在过去，对此有所了解。
But it is extraordinarily challenging to awaken that energy,
但要唤醒那股能量，
to make it uncoil itself and rise through the Sushumna Nadi,
让它自行解开盘绕 并透过中脉（Sushumna Nadi）上升，
which, at a gross level,
（中脉的粗糙层面是 由副交感神经系统所代表）
is represented by the parasympathetic nervous system.
这是非常具有挑战性的。
So, you mentioned every human being has this energy,
所以您提到每个人都有这种能量，
and you also mentioned that this energy helps us raise our consciousness.
您还提到这种能量 帮助我们提升意识。
So, I guess my question is then, why does every human being not evolve
那么，我想我的问题是， 为什么不是每个人都能进化
up to a certain level of consciousness?
到一定的意识水准？
Why is that different?
为什么会有这种差异？
That's again a wonderful question.
这又是一个绝妙的问题。
The reason is that this energy is a power that can be awakened, or is awakened,
原因是这种能量是一种力量， 只能通过一位大师的恩典唤醒，
only through the grace of a master. And unless and until there is a master
它才可以被唤醒，或者说被“唤”。 除非并且直到有一位大师
who has the, quote-unquote, authority or the ability to awaken it,
可以说，拥有“权威” 或能力去唤醒它，
this energy does not rise.
这种能量是不会上升的。
This energy, let's just say, has a mind of its own;
我们姑且说，这种能量 有它自己的思想；
that is because it is of divine origin.
那是因为它源于神圣。
It is divinity personified within a human being,
它是神性在 一个人内在的化身，
and that cannot be raised; that cannot come up;
而它无法被提升； 无法升起；
it doesn't uncoil itself and start rising just because somebody wants it to be so.
它不会仅仅因为某人希望它如此， 就自行解开盘绕并开始上升。
It has to happen, or it can only happen, if that individual, that said individual,
它必须发生，或者说它只能发生在 当那个个体，那个特定的个体，
comes in contact with a person who is a master and whose own energy is awakened to a state
接触到一位大师的人， 且其自身的能量已被唤醒到一种状态，
that can then allow for that other individual, who doesn't have it awakened,
那种状态可以允许另一个 尚未被唤醒的个体，
to be able to be awakened.
能够被唤醒。
We call it having a guru.
我们称之为拥有一位古鲁（guru 导师）。
It's a kind of traditional way of saying it, but it is only through the grace of the guru—
这是一种传统的说法， 但只有透过古鲁的恩典——
of a true guru, a primordial, a person who is truly a true master,
一位真正的古鲁，一位原始的， 一位真正的大师，
who has nothing but pure benevolence in his or her heart towards this other individual
他或她的心中对另一个个体 只有纯粹的仁慈，
can facilitate the awakening of this inner energy,
才能促成这种内在能量的唤醒，
which is very, very relatively straightforward in Sahaj,
这在霎哈嘉瑜伽中相对 非常直接，
but that experience we can have after this session,
但那种体验我们可以在 这次会谈后拥有，
as the session that is led by Shri Mataji herself.
在由锡吕·玛塔吉亲自 带领的环节中体验。
That's what I was going to say.
我正要这么说。
I think it is, on that note, perfect time for our audiences
我认为在这个节点上， 是我们的观众
to have that experience and then, just follow the instructions that the founder has,
拥有那种体验的完美时机，然后， 只需遵循创始人给出的指示，
because, like you mentioned, there has to be some expert or guru
因为，正如您所提到的，必须有 某个专家或古鲁
who has to be able to do this for you. And I would like to thank you, Dr. Ashish,
能够为您做到这一点。 我想感谢您，阿希什医生，
for your time today, and we look forward to talking to you again
感谢您今天的时间， 我们期待与您再次交谈，
on the next energy center in our subtle system,
探讨我们精微系统中的 下一个能量中心，
but thanks again for your time today.
但再次感谢您今天的时间。
Thank you very much.
非常感谢。
Great questions.
很好的问题。
Enjoyed it.
很享受。
Thank you.
谢谢。
I hope everybody enjoys the meditation session as well.
我希望大家也能享受 这次冥想环节。
Yes, we do hope that.
是的，我们确实希望如此。
Shri Mataji: Called as the Muladhara chakra, which manifests the pelvic plexus outside.
锡吕·玛塔吉：被称为根轮， 它在外部显化为骨盆神经丛。
Now, this center is placed below the Kundalini, which is placed in the sacrum bone.
现在，这个中心位于昆达里尼下方， 昆达里尼则位于荐骨中。
This is called sacrum because it is a sacred bone.
这被称为荐骨（sacrum）， 因为它是一块神圣的骨头（sacred bone）。
In this bone lies the Kundalini, the residual power of our germination.
在这块骨头里，存在着昆达里尼， 是我们生命萌发的剩余力量。
During the process of Kundalini awakening, you can see the pulsation down here.
在昆达里尼唤醒的过程中， 你可以看到这里的脉动。
You can also, through a stethoscope, see the rising of the Kundalini,
你也可以透过听诊器， 看到昆达里尼的上升，
and you can see the pulsation in the backbone till it reaches here in the fontanel bone area,
你可以在脊柱中看到脉动， 直到它到达这里的囟门骨区，
where it breaks through.
并在那里穿透出来。
At that point, you do not feel any pulsation.
在那一刻， 你感觉不到任何脉动。
As soon as this happens, from your hands, a cool breeze starts to flow.
一旦这发生了， 从你的手上，一股凉风开始流出。
You can feel it on your fingers, as shown here.
你可以在你的手指上感觉到它， 如此处所示。
These are the terminal points of the sympathetic nervous system within us.
这些是我们内在交感神经系统 的末端点。
These represent all the centers that are inside us,
这些代表了我们内在 所有的中心，
and you start feeling them on your fingers as absolutely your own experience.
你开始在你的手指上感觉到它们， 这完全是你自己的体验。
Keep your eyes closed.
请闭上眼睛。
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
首先，请把你的右手 放在你的心脏上。
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
左手一直朝向我。
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
现在，在这里，你必须在你的心中， 用全部的诚意说：母亲， 我就是那个灵（真我 spirit）吗？
Ask the question three times in your heart.
在你的心中问这个问题三次。
This is a very fundamental question.
这是一个非常根本的问题。
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
现在把右手 移到你胃部的左侧，
in the upper part.
在上方的位置。
Here press it.
在这里按住它。
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
现在，这是你的导师中心， 你的指引，你的古鲁 Tattva（导师原则）， 如人们所说。
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
所以问一个问题： 母亲，我是自己的导师吗？
This is the question to be asked three times.
这个问题要问三次。
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
现在把你的右手向下移动 到腹部的下部。
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
现在，这是所有神圣工作 完成的中心，
all the pure work is done.
所有纯粹的工作都从这里完成。
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
所以要问六次， 因为这个中心有六个花瓣，
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
母亲，请赐予我纯粹的真知。
Six times you just ask.
你就问六次。
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
作为这个请求的结果， 昆达里尼开始被唤醒。
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
现在，为了帮助昆达里尼上升， 你必须与她合作。
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
所以请把你的右手 放在左侧，
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
在你腹部的上部， 然后按在胃上。
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
现在，在这里， 为了帮助昆达里尼上升，
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
你必须充满信心地说： 母亲，我是自己的导师。
This you have to say ten times.
这句话你要说十次。
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
这是十条诫律， 你必须说：
that Mother, I am my own master.
母亲，我是自己的导师。
Now, ten times with full confidence.
现在，充满信心地说十次。
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
现在请把你的右手举到 你的心脏。
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
现在在这里，你必须说， 再次充满信心地说：
Mother, I am the Spirit.
母亲，我就是那个灵（真我）。
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
这是真理，你就是真我。
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
但你必须充满信心地说， 母亲，我就是那个灵。
This you have to say twelve times.
这句你要说十二次。
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
现在，人类必须知道， 全能的上帝是爱的海洋。
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
但最重要的是，祂是宽恕的海洋。
So He forgives.
所以祂会宽恕。
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
无论你做错了什么，祂都会宽恕。
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
所以不要感到内疚， 把你的右手交叉
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
放在左侧，在你的脖子和肩膀 形成的角落里。
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
现在在这里，你必须说， 再次充满信心地说十六次：
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
母亲，我没有罪疚感。
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
请说：母亲，我没有罪疚感。
Sixteen times.
十六次。
I am not guilty at all.
我完全没有罪疚感。
Please say it.
请把这句话说出来。
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
现在把你的手交叉放在你的前额上， 这是一个非常重要的中心。
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
在这里，你必须发自内心地说： 母亲，我宽恕每一个人。
Please say it from your heart.
请发自内心地说。
How many times is not the point.
说几次并不重要。
Mother, I forgive everyone.
母亲，我宽恕每一个人。
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
现在，有些人可能会说 宽恕很困难。
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
但这是一种幻象， 以为我们不宽恕或我们宽恕，
We do not do anything in both the cases.
在这两种情况下， 其实我们什么也没做。
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
但如果我们不宽恕， 我们就落入了坏人的圈套。
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
所以请诚心地说： 母亲，我宽恕每一个人。
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
现在请把你的手放在后脑勺， 也是同一个能量中心，在后脑部位，
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
让你的头靠在手上， 然后稍微向后推。
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
现在，在这里，你必须说， 为了让你自己安心……
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
因为你总是会感到内疚， 说：“哦，神圣的力量，如果我做错了任何事，
please forgive me.
请宽恕我。”
Please forgive me, from your heart.
请宽恕我。发自你的内心去说。
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
现在请将你的手完全伸直， 把你的手掌中心，
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
放在囟门骨区的顶端， 那是你童年时非常柔软的那块骨头。
Press it hard.
请用力按压它。
Press hard your scalp.
用力按压你的头皮。
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
现在你要转动你的手七次， 一边说这句话——这是你必须请求的：
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
母亲，请赐予我自觉， 因为我无法强加它给自己。
So you have to ask for it.
所以你必须诚心请求它。
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
转动七次，用力按压， 并且非常用力地转动七次。
Slowly saying that.
慢慢地，一边说着这句话。